Guide to the Incunabula Collection at Stanford University, 1467-1500
Department of Special Collections
- Gellius, Aulus. Aulus Gelius. [Noctes Atticae] Impressum Venetijs: A Philippo Pi[n]cio Ma[n]tuano, anno Domini 1500 die xv mensis Iulij [15 July 1500], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1500 .G45 F; [10], CXVIII leaves (last p. blank); 31 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., V, p. 499 (IB.23695). GW 10602. Goff (rev.), G-127. Hain-Copinger, 7527. ISTC (RLIN), ig00127000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: scattered red or blue initials. Binding: full leather; gilt decorated panelled spine with title label. Binder's title: Avlvs Gelivs. Provenance: ms. marginalia and emendations.
- Holy Roman Empire. Hernach volget dye Verschreibung so des Reichs Regiments Hilff vnd Ordnung halben: auff dem Reichstag zu Augspurg beschlossen vnnd auffgericht ist. Cited as: Ordnung des Reichsregiments[Nuremberg: Hieronymus Hltzel, after 10 Sept. 1500], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1500 .H65; 64 p. (last 3 p. blank); 29 cm.
  References: Indexed by: GW (Nachtr.), 362. - Indexed by: Goff (rev.), M-395. - Indexed by: ISTC (RLIN), im00395000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Imperfect: 1st leaf (blank) lacking. Binding: vellum over boards; property label on upper cover. Provenance: Rud. Hildebrand (signature); The Hildebrand Library (ink-stamp); ms. marginalia.
- Peniteas cito libellus iste nuncupatur: tractans compendiose de penitentia et eius circu[m]stantiis ac vitam peccatis deprauatam emendare cupientibus multu[m] vtilis et necessari[us].[Metz: Kaspar Hochfeder, about 1500], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1500 .P64; [32] (last 2 p. blank) p.; 21 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., III, p. 664 (IA.12725). Goff (rev.), P-848. Hain-Copinger, 13158. ISTC (RLIN), ip00848000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: untouched. Binding: quarter red cloth; brown boards; title label on upper cover. Provenance: R. Hildebrand (signature); The Hildebrand Library (ink-stamp).
- Schedel, Hartmann, 1440-1514. Das Bch der Croniken vnnd Geschichten: mit Figuren vnd Pildnussen von Anbeginn der Welt bis auff dise vnsere Zet. Gedruckt vn[d] vole[n]t in d[er] kayserlichen Statt Auspurg: Durch Han[n]sen Schnsperger, Im Iar nach Cristi Geburt vnsers Herren, 1500., Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1500 .S315 f; CCCXVII, [15] leaves (last leaf blank): ill.; 31 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., II, p. 375 (IB.6422). Goff (rev.), S-311. Hain-Copinger, 14512. ISTC (RLIN), is00311000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Imperfect: both blank leaves lacking. Binding: blind-stamped pigskin over boards; panelled spine; remnants of clasps.
- Speculum sapientie Beati Cirilli Episcopi alias quadripartitus apologieticus vocat[us]: in cuius quide[m] puerbiis omnis [et] totius sapie[n]tie speculum claret: feliciter incipit.[Paris: Etienne Jehannot for Jean Petit, ca. 1500], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1500 .S63 T; [144] p.; 14 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent. VIII, p. 200 (IA.40929) Goff (rev.), C-1021. ISTC (RLIN), ic01021000. Proctor, 8371-A.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Binding: full calf, gilt panels on upper and lower covers and spine; embossed armorial crest on upper cover with motto: gang forward; vignette stamped in blind on lower cover; marbled endpapers. Binder: J. Mackenzie Son (stamp). Provenance: Gulielmi Stirling (armorial bookplate); ANA c. Keir (booklabel).
- Staupitz, Johann von, d. 1524. Decisio questionis de audientia misse in parrochiali ecclesia Dominicis et festivis diebus: cum ceteris annexis.[Tubingen]: Johann Otmar, [after 30 Mar. 1500], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1500 .S8; [16] p. (last p. blank); 18 cm.
  References: Goff (rev.), S-761. Hain 15052. ISTC (RLIN), is00761000. Stillwell S677.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Binding: gray paper boards; in slipcase, with spine title: Staupitz. Provenance: R. Hildebrand, 1851 (signature); Coenobij [Irebensis?] (inscription).